hi in the previous video about spline and curves what we've studied was the
Bezier curve and when we started to extend the Bezier curve to do a spline
and to attach several Bezier curves back to back what happened is that we were
sharing the first and last point and we were only sharing that one so we had a
discontinuity in our curve if you remember this shape we had here the
the first point, basically the tangent going in that direction for the first
basic curve and then the tangent we want to get to get it to go in this
direction for the second tangent so we don't have that discontinuities because
we have different angle here. It is quite annoying to compute every time to
make sure that you know that your previous points and the next point would
actually be on a line so you have continuity inside of your curve and so
So for this, what we will do is instead of parametrizing our curve using the four points,
what we want to do is to be able to parametrize it using only the first and the last point
and then giving directly the tangent we want to use.
So saying I want it to go in that direction and then the second point will go in that
direction and then we will be sharing that point and tangent to the next one and that
And Salo has to more easily make sure that we have continuity between those stuff.
So this type of curve now is what we call an Hermit curve.
And the Hermit curve is basically defined as this, is defined as the endpoints and as
the tangent, so basically as the derivative of the endpoints.
So we now have the points and the first derivative
of those points, the value we want to give to our function.
Before being able to compute this, what we will have to do
is to understand how we could do it just doing polynomial.
And we will start from those mathematics,
and then we will build the mid-curve after it.
So if we want to fit a polynomial
through a certain set of points,
you could actually fit any type of polynomial
of a certain degrees to the number of points degree n plus 1.
So if I have a cubic polynomial,
I can fit it to go through four points.
And again, as we were doing cubic,
mainly I will focus on those cubic.
So let's say that I will have, in this case,
if it agrees to do it, I have those four points
and I want to define a curve, a cubic curve
that will go through those four points.
How we do this is that we start from the cubic function
and the cubic function itself, you know,
is the ATQ plus BT square plus CT plus D.
So that's a cubic functions,
the generic form of the cubic functions.
So what do we know from the points we actually want to match?
We know that when my function is at T zero,
the value will be two.
When a function is at T one, the value will be one.
At T three, the value will be four.
And at T four, the value will be one again.
So I can have those as the values I would want to compute.
And now what I can do is that I can actually
substitute the 0, 1, 3, and 4 through these functions, which
give us that d, because all the 0s will make everything
disappear, d equals 2.
And then everything will be 1, 1, 1.
So a, b, c, and d, a plus b plus c plus d equal 1.
add in the cube, 27, 9, 3, plus D equal 4,
and same for 4, 64, 16, 4, and D equal 1.
So that give us basically a system of four equations
and four unknown.
Now, that's something that we could easily solve.
And so I will just put those,
there was equation in the matrix form,
and basically I have the 2141 equal my big matrix
coming from here, the D comes from the first one,
A, B, C, D, one, one, one, one, 27, nine, three,
coming the next nine and so on and so on,
and I get the A, B, C, D.
And now that I have my matrix form,
I can actually solve for A, B, C, D,
and to solve through A, B, C, D.
What I will do in this case is just use
the linear algebra solve method from NumPy
that would just solve this for me.
And in my case now, I have the A, B, C and D parameters
coming from the cubic.
And if I replace A, B, C, D with those values,
now I can actually have a function
that will go through my four points.
So that's how you compute this kind of polynomial.
polynomial. Now that I have this and we understand how we could actually use the system of equation
and to build them and having our functions or polynomial goes through a bunch of points,
what we can do is we can start to look at the Hermit curve definition itself.
And to start with the Hermit curve, what we will have to do is basically remember that we will be
doing cubic Hermit curve again, same way. And so I'm starting from the cubic function again,
so atq plus bt square plus ct plus d. And I will just rewrite them this as a matrix form. So it's
basically exactly the same thing except that I've put them in a matrix form but
it's the same formula do not worry about this one and what we will be doing now
is again do as usual as the basic curve and all of that kind of stuff we will
say that the amide curve is parametrized between 0 and 1 and that will
make our life way easier. Now we could do an interpolation saying that at time zero we will be at
point zero. At time one we will be at point one and then at time zero we want to have the derivative
of point zero and at time one we want the derivative of point one. So what happened when you do this
is that we actually compute also the derivative of our function. So that's my cubic functions and
and that's the derivative of the cumming function.
If you don't remember, you take the derivative,
you bring the three in front and do minus one.
So I get three AT square plus BT plus C and the D disappear.
So that's the derivative itself.
And now the same way as we've done
when we were doing the polynomial,
what we could do is substitute the different values
for the different ABCD.
So I will have 0.08 again.
Everything will be zero, so 0.001 for D.
At 0.1, everything will be at one.
And then I will have the derivative of the 0.0.
Again, I will put zero in these functions now.
So everything disappeared except the C.
And I'll have the derivative at 0.1,
and then I will have three, two, one,
and zero, the D has disappeared.
So basically now I have the same system of equation
as we had before, except that now it takes 0.1,
the derivative of 0.0 and derivative of 0.1.
And then we could solve for ABCD again.
I said that this time I will not solve it numerically
because I'm still trying to find the functions itself.
So I will solve it by how we actually solve
this kind of system usually.
And to solve for ABCD, what we do is that we take
the inverse of the matrix in the middle.
So if you take the inverse of the matrix,
now ABCD equal the inverse of the matrix,
that's my minus one, multiplied by the point 0.1
and both derivatives.
And if I compute that inverse,
So that's my matrix, compute the inverse.
I end up with this matrix.
So I could actually write it in the function directly.
I get the ABCD equal that matrix multiplied by 0.1
derivative and derivative.
And now we have our ABCD here.
What we could do with that is that remember
that we've wrote the ABCD, the function itself
itself as a matrix of times multiplied by a b c d so I can substitute the same way again
my a b c d remove it completely and only keep the the times the matrix in the middle and my
points so point zero point one both derivative remember this formula this shape is really close
to the one we were using when we said that we want to do
matrix form for Bezier curve. See that's the same except that the matrix is
different and here we used p1, p2, p3 and p4
but basically it is the same
the same comm set now that is 0.0, 0.1 and both derivatives.
What we have here is
The formula, if we were actually computing everything, again you get the 0.0 multiplied
by this, 0.1 multiplied by this, the derivative multiplied by this, and the derivative multiplied
by this.
And that gives us the Hermit curve, and I can now see, I've used the formula, the one
I've computed here, not the matrix form.
I've computed the formula, and I've used 0.0,
two times, times cubed, minus three,
times squares, and all that kind of stuff.
And you could see that basically it works now.
I have my points, my derivative, I get the curves,
and I reach here my points towards my derivative.
That's a 1D example.
So for zero to one, I have two values.
And I can do the same for a 2D example.
So instead of having a point that just defined as t at the bottom and having a value for y,
I can have an xy points and xy points and then my t, my parameter is 0, 1 will give me
the curve the same way we did the Bezier curve.
And you can see now, what we have here is a 2D example.
So I have the direction in which I want the curve to go.
And I get the curve to go through my parameters, my 0 to 1.
And it's in a 2D space.
And that's what the Amit curve is computing.
Now there is, of course, as we define the Hermit curve,
where you said that it's another way to compute a curve
that goes between points and have tangents.
There is a link between how we computed the basic curve
and what we're doing here with the Hermit curve.
And basically, the formula to go from one to the other
is this, is if you
If you have a bunch of
Hermit, so you will have two points the point zero and point one and you get both
Derivative to get back the four points of the basic of the only thing you do is that you take the first point as being the first point
The last one has been the last one and then point one of my basic curve is point zero plus
a third of the derivative of
of 0.0 and 0.2 is the 0.1 minus a third of the derivative.
That divided by three will come in logically a bit later
when we talk about a few, the stuff.
But right now, just remember that we divide by three
to get the right point in this case.
So to show you that it works, what I could do,
it's basically starting from that 2D example again I have my 2D example I
have the Bezier what I have the Hermit curve that is the black one and so by
using the Hermit curve now I can actually put my points here you know see
that's a third of my derivative and I get the points there for my second point
and the third point is a third of the derivative less and I get my point here
And that's the basic curve and that's the blue dots and you can see that they're perfectly aligned. So
they both are
Computing exactly the same thing just a bit differently again on how you do it
And now if I want to do an omit spline, so I want to actually put a bunch of hermit curves back to back
then I can just share not only the last and the first point, but also the
tangent and say I will have a continuous function instantly. What I will do is I
will rearrange a few of the parameters, you know, because when we build the
matrix the first time when we said it was 0.0, 0.1, first the derivative of 0.0,
derivative of 0.1. But if I want to share the data between a bunch of curves, it would make
more sense if in my data I had 0.0 derivative of 0.0 0.1 derivative of 0.1. So I can just move
forward inside of my list of points in derivative and I can build a spline this way. So this is
This is what I've done. I've used the matrix form, except that I've swapped the column,
so I will get a point derivative point derivative point derivative, and I can just directly reuse
this to have a complete list, to have a list of hermit curves that goes back to
back. So if I define now my list of points as a points and a derivative of points
and derivative points and derivative, I can have this hermit curve that goes
through a bunch of points. And so this was the video about the Hermit curve
and Hermit spline and in the next one we will go through how to compute a bunch
of stuff automatically to do what we call the cardinal spline that will make
our life easier when we want to use a Hermit curve. See you next time.